<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Politics | CorgaLabs Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://cmceniry.github.com/blog/categories/politics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://cmceniry.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-03-26T22:18:55-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://cmceniry.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Chris McEniry]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Carbonite CEO on Rush Limbaugh]]></title>
    <link href="http://cmceniry.github.com/blog/2012/03/04/carbonite-ceo-on-rush-limbaugh/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-04T14:38:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://cmceniry.github.com/blog/2012/03/04/carbonite-ceo-on-rush-limbaugh</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Whether you sit on the Left or the Right, or the left or the right, or
the middle, or the Middle, or underneath it all or wherever, I would
really appreciate if the discourse that we had didn't resolve to
namecalling based on ignorance. I know that that doesn't help get
money<sup>Wsupport</sup> for elections, but it keeps me from adding to the
"Don't want to live on this planet anymore" meme. If you don't
understand how that's connected, please read
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Republic-Lost-Money-Corrupts-Congress/dp/0446576433">Lessig</a>.</p>

<p>So, it makes me feel good to see that
<a href="http://www.carbonite.com/en/blog/A-Message-from-Carbonite-CEO-David-Friend-Regarding-Ads-on-Limbaugh">Carbonite</a>,
not only pulled their support for Limbaugh, but also will not continue
even in light of Limbaugh's apology. Given multiple hyperbolic
statements by Limbaugh in the past, I don't feel any sincerity. On the
other hand, I feel that Friend is sincere:</p>

<pre><code>“No one with daughters the age of Sandra Fluke, and I have two,
could possibly abide the insult and abuse heaped upon this
courageous and well-intentioned young lady. Mr. Limbaugh, with his
highly personal attacks on Miss Fluke, overstepped any reasonable
bounds of decency. Even though Mr. Limbaugh has now issued an
apology, we have nonetheless decided to withdraw our advertising
from his show. We hope that our action, along with the other
advertisers who have already withdrawn their ads, will ultimately
contribute to a more civilized public discourse.”
</code></pre>

<p>But even if I assume it's a marketing move, it's a marketing move that
puts the discussion in the right direction.</p>

<p>Friend is putting his money where his mouth is; I think I have to do
so as well (even if I don't have a completely good use case for it for
me).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
