<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Enterpise | CorgaLabs Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://cmceniry.github.com/blog/categories/enterpise/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://cmceniry.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-03-03T23:04:17-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://cmceniry.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Chris McEniry]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[In which Pooh is shown how 'Enterprise' can be a bug instead of a feature...]]></title>
    <link href="http://cmceniry.github.com/blog/2012/03/03/in-which-pooh-is-shown-how-enterprise-can-be-a-bug-instead-of-a-feature-dot-dot-dot/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-03T22:43:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://cmceniry.github.com/blog/2012/03/03/in-which-pooh-is-shown-how-enterprise-can-be-a-bug-instead-of-a-feature-dot-dot-dot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was in a meeting the other day with a storage vendor selling their
wares. He asked what we had at the time, and I let him know, and was
extremely surprised by his response.</p>

<p>"We're using X," I said.</p>

<p>"Oh, well, that's nice, but if you want an Enterprise solution, you
really need to be using ours," he spouted off smuggly.</p>

<p>At which point, I had to say something. "It's statements like that
that are why nobody likes [your company]."</p>

<p>My boss laughed, I think mostly to defuse it a bit, but he also said
"He's not kidding."</p>

<p>And I wasn't. I really think that if you want to come into my house
and try to sell me something, the number one thing you do is not
insult me and what I currently have. At least, don't try it until you
have an idea of how I feel about the solution. In this case, it wasn't
that I was tied to it, but that that's what we had, plain and simple.</p>

<p>The second thing that you may want to do is say something that
actually adds value, not just belittles the competition. Ok, so let's
assume that Enterprise is a good thing - why is your solution more
Enterprise than what we have? In this case, he eventually added that
it was twice as fast as our current solution.</p>

<p>Which leads me to the third thing you may want to do. Don't try to
sell on facts taken out of context. Ok, so it's twice as fast. It's
also 4 years newer technology. According to Moore's Law applied to
storage, if you're only twice as fast, you're half or a quarter of
where you should be on the progression curve.</p>

<p>So, what does Enterprise mean? Based on the vendor comments, it's:</p>

<ul>
<li>Better than what we have right now,</li>
<li>Just something we should trust the vendor on, and</li>
<li>Behind on the technology curve.</li>
</ul>


<p>Great sales job.</p>

<p>I think of the other "Enterprise" products that we have. Usually,
there's one or more of the additional features:</p>

<ul>
<li>Complex licensing model - $ per core up to this rate, and then $$ per
core past that, but only if you have X amount of RAM, or it was
purchased on a Blue Moon.</li>
<li>Manual installation - It requires a GUI to install, can't be
automated (even with something like a response file), and sometimes
you have to do parallel steps and hope that they don't have race
conditions or start over when they do.</li>
<li>Inflexible - "You can do other things with it, but that would be a
custom setup and unsupported."</li>
<li>Long patch cycles - This would be fine if we all didn't already know
that half of what's out there is commodity open source software. It
doesn't matter you've wrapped it all up under an appliance bow -
it's still vulnerable to whatever it is that the patch is for.</li>
<li>Lots of fingerpointing when it doesn't interact correctly in my
owner situation or with other Enterprise software.</li>
</ul>


<p>So, what is Enterprise software? It can't be software that we're
paying for the quality of. What it really comes down to - it's
software that we can outsource the blame to... if we're lucky.</p>

<p>This doesn't mean that there isn't good Enterprise software out
there. Just means that what is good out there probably isn't being
bought for the reasons that it's being marketed for.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
